Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 4p.; Castrioto, Felix Antony. Lisbon
    Has received no answer to his letters; such neglect is not merited by the first foreigner who undertook in public defence of America, and who made a deep impression on many people's minds by his pamphlets on the justice of the American cause; only desires the opportunity to render himself useful to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre, Martinique
    Recommending Richard Harrison, who has rendered essential service as agent for the States of Virginia and Maryland; his intention is to enter a commercial establishment at Cadiz; refers Franklin to him for a full and candid report of the situation of affairs in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Opinion of the Grand Facteur and M. Van Berkel as regards the enactment of the resolution granting unlimited convoys.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sequel of Sir J[oseph] Y[orke]'s affair with the Leyden Gazatte. Hopes concerning Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Promising to do all he can for M. Dubourg. Certain small matters of business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Persuaded Capt. Stephen Marchant, of the "Black Prince," to postpone his sailing until he received an answer from Franklin to his letter of the 28th ult.; the Captain, however, interprets Franklin's silence as permission to take the packets, and will sail as soon as weather permits, trusting to Franklin's assistance to have the prizes condemned to his profit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Sayre, Stephen. Amsterdam
    Concerning the plan in his former letter relative to Ireland; assured by certain gentlemen in London that nothing is needed but a small fleet under a proper person, commissioned from America; trusts Franklin would not consider him an improper person for this business; discusses the plan in detail. Arrival of Mr. Van der Capellen in Amsterdam to sound the city with regard to America; a strong party in her favor. Desires to know if he is to receive no countenance or support from America; others are supported, after accusations, which, if true, ought to hang them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Amsterdam's attitude and that of M. Van Berkel in the affair of the convoys. Rumored offers of friendship from Ireland to America. Belief that Spain's declaration is imminent. Arrival of the "Independence" from Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 9; L.S. John Jay, President. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    In accordance with resolutions of Congress, bills of exchange have been drawn to the amount of 350,000 livres, to be expended in France for military stores. But should hopes of obtaining the supplies in the French West Indies be realized the bills will not be presented for payment. Accompanied by extracts from the minutes of Congress, attested by Cha[rle]s Thomson, Secretary, containing the resolutions (1 p.).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 24; L. 16p.; Noemer, Pieter (Petrus) van. ZiericzÉe
    Interest he takes in the promise that America will be a refuge for the oppressed of all the world; the determination of himself and his unfortunate companions to escape there as to a sanctuary. Recounts in detail his life and the misfortunes of his political career in Switzerland. Desires to be informed of the best city in which to settle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Sears, David. Amsterdam
    Announcing the arrival of the sloop "Independence" from Virginia, belonging to Mr. Isaac Sears and Co. of Boston; expects to return to America on this vessel and begs to be the bearer of despatches. Hears that Mr. Adams and the Marquis de la Fayette went out in the fleet of M. La Motte Picquet, but being damaged in a storm were obliged to return; hopes it is not true.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, William. Frankfort
    Repeats request that he endeavor to obtain from the French Ministry military stores for the State of Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Boston
    His long and fatiguing trip back to Virginia; the vessel by which he forwarded Franklin's letters to Congress was unfortunately lost or taken. Anxious to return to France, if Franklin can offer him any employment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 6p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Boston
    Copy of preceding with an added postscript, giving an account of the repulse of the British, on May 14th, by Gen. Moultrie at Charleston; the ravaging and burning of defenseless towns by the enemy exasperates instead of intimidating the people; its probable result.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Bek, -----. Vienna
    Desires to find employment in America and end his days there; his studies in philosophy and jurisprudence; refers to M. de Vergennes for his character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Morel, -----. Versailles
    Asks for further remuneration for his maps, having only received one louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Dubuisson, Paul-Ulrich. Paris
    Has waited to receive some acknowledgement from Franklin of a copy of his work entitled "Abrégé de la Révolution de l'Amérique Anglaise"; although his work has had a fairly flattering reception, Franklin's silence on the subject has made him regret more than once having undertaken the work; without Franklin's approval and encouragement, is determined not to enter upon another work concerning the events in America during the past year.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Demezaudré, -----. St Malo
    Announcing the arrival of a ship from Carolina with news of the taking of Savannah by the English, who were making ready to march upon Charleston; incredible dearness of all clothing and provisions in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Concerning their attempt to get subscribers on the papers Franklin intrusted them with; expects the arrival shortly of M. Van der Capellen; will consult with him as to what might be done for the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Has just received two letters from Maryland; encloses copies of both, and earnestly desires Franklin's advice as to the possibility of taking up the money in France.
  - to --, 1779 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Lovell, Langford. Antigua
    Desiring a recommendation to the Governor of Dominica; since the conquest of the island, has acted in every respect as a neutral.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Manner in which the affair of Sir J[oseph] Y[orke] and the Leyden Gazette terminated. Arrival of letters from London consenting to Holland's commercial relations with France, provided she does not send them timber.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Gedike, L.F.G.E. Berlin
    Wants to aid in the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Byrne, Edward. Cherbourg
    Desires to be released from imprisonment and sent back to Philadelphia; his uncle keeps "The Sign of the Ship" in Walnut Street.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Anderson, George. Lisbon
    Introduces Arnold Henry Dohrman, whose character and proceedings towards the American cause he has before described. Enclosed is a letter to the same purport addressed to Mons. Guillaume [Jno. G.] Frazer, Bordeaux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Kendrick, John. Lisbon
    Commanded the brig "Comte d'Estaing" when it was captured by the English; put ashore on one of the islands near Spain; his subsequent arrival at Lisbon; the kindness he and his companions received from Arnold Henry Dohrman, who furnished them with clothes and money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    The situation of things in Congress makes him daily expectant of interesting decisions to communicate to Franklin; matters agitated but not as yet concluded respecting Franklin's commission. Enclosing a copy of a Resolution of Congress, desiring an account of the Commissioners' proceedings in M. Beaumarchais's accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Mante, Thomas. Paris
    Owing to Franklin's two guineas paid to the concierge of the prison, is allowed to keep the chamber in which he is lodged; cannot describe the horrid situation from which Franklin's generosity has extricated him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Fight in the Assembly over the Resolution to grant unlimited convoys; splendid part played by Amsterdam; her rival Rotterdam forced to acknowledge it also; the G[rand] P[ensionnaire] likely to regret the role he has played.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 Aug. 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Honoré, André. Paris
    United to Franklin by the secret and powerful bonds of the brotherhood; is in great distress; his efforts to gain a livelihood; begs Franklin to assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 15; D. 2p.; The Board of Treasury
    Schedule of 50 sets of bills of exchange dated June 15, 1779, and payable three years later.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Berail, Peter. Cette
    Desiring to represent the thirteen United States in the above harbor, either as Consul or Commissary; his present position as quay-master; desires that his son, who has learned English, may have the reversion of the said Consulship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Report received of the "Queen of France," the "Warren" and the "Ranger" having taken a small fleet of transports laden with arms and stores; the officers on board sent to Boston. Hopes the operations of Spain will cause a fall in insurances and admit of the resuming of trade with the United States.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1779 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Sends the two busts of Dr. Franklin; the bearer will receive the amount due on them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Paris
    Concerning the commission, instructions and other papers for the cutter "Black Prince," commanded by Stephen Marchant and owned by Mr. John Torris; the said privateer sailed for Dunkirk on the 11th inst.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Stockton, Samuel W. Amsterdam
    Expects to sail on the 26th in a small vessel bound for Philadelphia or Baltimore; promises to take the best care of any letters or despatches Franklin may entrust him with.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Pine, Joseph. Josselin
    Was a passenger on board a merchantman bound for Newfoundland, where he was captured by an American privateer; was given his freedom, only to be once more taken prisoner by a French frigate; begs Franklin to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Account of a little scene between Mr. Sayre and de N[eufville], ending in the former's leaving with a displeased air; possible harm Mr. Sayre may do.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Baudouin, -----. Longchamps
    M. de Sartine has just heard that an American privateer ["The Black Prince"], is about to intercept the packets from Dover to Calais, and that the Captain, having communicated this project to Franklin interpreted his silence to mean consent; M. de Sartine begs Franklin to write at once to this Captain to abstain from attacking any packet from Dover to Calais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Peter Vesey and others. Bouling Boulogne?
    On their way to Boston were taken prisoners by the English, and later, having obtained a passage to Halifax, they were captured by a French cutter; beg to be released from their imprisonment and suffered to go board any American ship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    In a few weeks expects to send to Franklin everything complete relative to an edition of his papers; plans to use a certain engraving of Franklin and the motto, "His country's friend, but more of human kind." Has got the preface of G[alloway]'s speech; his examination in the House; his testimony concerning the beginning of the rebellion, and also of facts relative to recruiting in England and America. Little effect produced by the Spanish manifesto; reason for this. Attitude of the English Ministry towards America and Ireland. Letter from Gov. F. stated to contain accounts of the difficulty America experienced in getting and supporting an army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, Alexander John. St. Germain
    Desires to communicate some letters which have passed between a friend of Franklin's and himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 17; A.L.S. 5p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Conversations held on the American cause by Messrs. Van der Capellen, Dumas and several American gentlemen. Discusses in detail the question of the loan for Congress. Hopes the conclusion of that treaty is not far off which will unite forever the twenty States in two republics.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning M. de N[eufville]'s letter asking permission to apply to Congress for the title of United States Treasurer in Holland. Hopes to celebrate with Franklin the joyful anniversary of July 4th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 18; A.L.S. 3p.; De Fraÿ, Madame. Paris
    Begging that the enclosed letter may be forwarded to her husband, a captain in the service of America; none of her letters have apparently reached him since his departure.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 June 19; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the State of New Jersey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 19; L.S. John Jay, President. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Order to pay Caron de Beaumarchais 20,000 livres, pursuant to resolutions of Congress of June 5, 1779.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    Announcing the favorable termination of certain proceedings in law. The old secret of making the famous Greek fire which can destroy a fleet at a great distance; the Comte de Rostaing has made the experiment successfully.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse (Gamache), comtesse de Forbach and duchesse douairière de
    Sending Franklin the scissors she promised him; always delighted at an opportunity to recall herself to Franklin's thoughts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    News received of Gen. Clinton's having detached 3000 men upon an expedition; Gen. Washington has apprized the Governor of Virginia of the fact, supposing the attack to be planned against that State. Concerning the capture by the Americans of a frigate with 26,000 pounds sterling worth of Indian goods on board, a seasonable and important supply for the use of the States. Size of the English fleet which is assembled at St. Helena and ready to put to sea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Allemand, -----. Paris
    Forwards Franklin the note he asked for; reproaches himself for the trouble Franklin is so willing to take in aiding him to perfect his work on canals.
    [Appended is a note in Franklin's hand concerning canals in America.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Magellan (Magalhaens), Jean-Hyacinthe de. London
    Asking Franklin to obtain the release of Richard Nairne, Captain of a merchant vessel, taken by the French frigate "Flora"; Mr. Nairne's brother in London will do all in his power to aid him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Warns him against two persons whose seal for America may do more harm than good. [M. de Neufville and the Baron de C.] Presented Messrs. [Sir John] Pringle and [Samuel W.] Stockton to the French Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] June 22; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Sends the newspaper containing the Spanish declaration of war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    The union of the two fleets at Corunna leaves no longer in doubt the resolution of Spain. Arrival of an American vessel at Bilbao with many prisoners, as well as four prizes. Expects great feats from Capt. Jones. Names and dates of sailing of many vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 23; A.L.S. 5p.; Merchant, Stephen. On board the "Black Prince."
    Account of his cruise in the "Black Prince" and the prizes he captured; sends a list of the prisoners he took, and also of the men taken from him by the English; an equal number; hopes Franklin can arrange an exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Holtzendorff, Louis-Casimir, baron de. Paris
    The severe illness of young Mr. Cochran; as his father is very much esteemed by Franklin, thinks he would be grateful if a good surgeon or doctor were sent to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Duvivier, -----. Paris
    Is called away suddenly to Havre; the bearer has not heard from his father for twenty years and desires to send him a letter; begs Franklin to give him the necessary instructions for forwarding.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Jenings, Edmund. Paris
    Acknowledges Franklin's kind invitation for dinner to celebrate the anniversary of the declaration of American independency; unable to accept owing to his departure on his intended tour; will keep the day, however, in his remembrance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; De la Verdière, -----. Paris
    Sends Franklin a copy of his memoir.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Effect on England and Holland of Spain's declaration. de N[eufville] too ambitious. Baron de C. busy publishing letters he received from prominent Americans; has too little power and too much rashness to be of service; loan proposed by his friend, Lieut.-Col. [J.G.] Diriks. Offered his services to the Spanish Envoy, M. Herreria. Vigorous Resolution passed in the Holland Assembly in accordance with Amsterdam's advice; sad figure cut by Sir J[oseph] Y[orke].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Amsterdam
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 13th inst., containing his sentiments on the two American bank notes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Thompson, Farley and Co. Nantes
    Desiring to know if Dr. Busch is still in Paris, as he has charge of some letters and papers directed to them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Steele, Joshua. London
    The political differences between their Nations cannot make him forget his affection and esteem for Franklin. Sends him forty copies of an abstract of the claim of five candidates for the premium offered by the Society [of Arts] for an invariable standard of weights and measures; makes suggestions for the distribution of these copies. Hopes that a ray of good sense will still be left to bring back peace and put a stop to miseries which degrade and disgrace them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 June 25; A.L. 2p.; C-----, -----. London
    Thanks Franklin for the kind reception given to his son. Wishes the detestable war was over. Assures him of the love and esteem of his friends in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 June 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Places the enclosed letter in Franklin's care; Mr. Stephenson, a friend of America, is the gentleman who waited upon Franklin at Passy, eighteen months before.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Green, Jno. Bordeaux
    Sailed from Philadelphia, the 2d of May, in the brigantine "Nesbitt"; captured by an English cruiser; his crew delivered up to the press-gang; made his escape and arrived in Bordeaux the preceding night; committed all his packets and letters to the sea. Beēfore he left Philadelphia, Capt. [John Burroughs] Hopkins, of the ship "Warren." captured a rich prize bound for Georgia; believed that the British will soon evacuate that State. News received of a famine in Bermuda.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1779 June 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dunkirk
    Steps he has taken in one or two cases to have American prisoners released; wishes to prove to his countrymen in Ireland that his support of the libertics of America has been noticed by Franklin. Cannot recommend the persons who wrote to Franklin from Belfast, until he has discovered something more definite concerning their character, names and designs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Montleger, ------. Port Louis
    Important affairs must have prevented Franklin from acting in the case of the Duchesse Rosnarko, who desires to obtain the amount due her son, killed on board the frigate "Reprisal" in the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Frazer, Jno G. Bordeaux
    Writes on behalf of an unfortunate countryman now a prisoner at Aix in Provence; his desire to return to Virginia and render some service to his country; his account of how he was forced into the service of the English is true in every particular.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Montgomery, Robert.
    Has always subscribed himself a subject of the United States, yet the day before, on a proclamation of war being made against England, he was arrested, his property seized, and his house filled with soldiers; in vain he produced his certificate and passport given him by Dr. Franklin and Mr. Lee, they obtained him no relief; writes to Franklin for further credentials, that he may be released from this distressing situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Couteulx and Cie. Paris
    Enclosing a letter from Messrs. de la Torre; begs Franklin to recommend this firm to Congress, and give his advice as to the quickest means of obtaining justice in this affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 26; A.L. in 3d P.; Arthur, Lee. Paris
    Informing Franklin that he will wait upon him on the 5th of July, and asking for an authenticated copy of the letter from the Commissioners to the Comte de Vergennes, concerning the agreement with Hortalez and Co., as well as a copy of his Excellency's answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival of Capt. John Green on the 23d inst., having been captured by a privateer; disappointment and loss incident to these miscarriages. A courier from Madrid has just passed through Bordeaux on his way to Versailles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Coffin, Alexander. Amsterdam
    Indorsing in the highest terms the model of a ship contrived by Mr. Sayre, which he thinks an improvement on any ship hitherto known; advantage such ships would be to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Letters from London say that the Ministry and the people are under great apprehension of an invasion, and the possible destruction of their commerce; measures the English are taking to guard against such an event.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 28; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam